English learners,
I had the idea today of walking around
while doing today's video. I'm here at a
park and I'm going to do a video where I
speak at normal speed.
Hopefully you guys like this format.
Hopefully you can hear me okay.
Obviously there might be some ambient
sounds. There's
landscapers here mowing the lawn.
There's kids playing and stuff like
that. So hopefully you can hear me well.
Today I want to talk about reasons why
you probably didn't learn English very
well when you took classes in school,
when you took English classes in high
school,
middle school, elementary school,
whatever it may be.
>> [clears throat]
>> This is
strange format for me so excuse me if
I'm just like
looking around. I'm trying to like be
natural here. I think people are
watching me so this is a little bit new
for me so bear with me here. But today I
want to talk about why you might not
have learned English very well in
school.
I'm also going to release a podcast
episode about this. Probably going to
come out in a couple months or so. I'm
way more ahead on podcast episodes than
I am on YouTube videos. But
I wanted to talk about this today
because it's a topic that is pretty
relevant to probably most of you, maybe
almost all of you. I'm sure most of you
learned English in school.
Maybe you took four years of English
classes in high school or maybe you took
even more than that if you started
English classes in middle school,
elementary school, whatever it may be.
But I hear this story again and again
and again every time I talk to students
about their experience learning English
in school, especially in public schools.
I'm not really talking here about
private schools. There's a lot of good
private schools. But in public schools
what tends to happen is that people take
years and years of English classes and
they never learn English. So why is
that? Let's talk about some of the
issues. These are just my opinions
obviously. Other people might disagree
with me. They might think that there are
other issues or they might not see it
the way I see it. But these are the
the things that I see that might
contribute to
the reasons why people don't learn
English in school. I don't have my notes
with me. Usually I have like my notes on
my computer to kind of keep me
organized. So I'm just kind of going off
the cuff here. Like I'm just trying to
speak naturally, spontaneously and try
to remember the ideas that I have in
mind. So I think the main idea
the not the main idea but the main
point, the main problem that I would say
of why
you know English classes aren't that
useful in the school. They're useful but
not as useful as we'd like them to be
is because they don't teach you how to
learn English, right? It would be great
if English classes in high school,
English teachers taught students how to
actually learn a language, how to
actually go about learning English
because the majority of our learning
comes outside of the classroom, right?
The classroom is not where we're getting
like most of our practice, most of our
listening practice perhaps not even most
of our speaking practice depending on
your situation. So because of that I'm
going to turn around here. I'm going to
like do laps at this park. Sorry, this
is like completely natural video, not
edited or anything like that. So
bear with me. But um
like I said one of the big problems
with English classes in high school,
middle school or whatever is that
students kind of just show up hoping to
learn English. They don't actually know
they don't actually learn how to learn a
language. You know whatever subject it
may be, it's great to learn how to learn
something, right? And when you learn how
to learn then you can do it on your own,
right? You don't need someone to guide
you through every step of the way or
whatever. But that's not the case in
high school English classes in most
countries, right? People don't learn how
to actually learn English. They just
show up and hopefully you know the
knowledge just like gets transferred to
their head from the teacher or whatever
and that's not how it works in most
cases, right? So that's a big issue is
that students aren't taught how to
learn. Another issue I would say is that
the content that is used is not always
the best. And so
I always talk about this idea of having
comprehensible input. That's the term
that's used nowadays to describe this.
Input referring to things that you
listen to or that you read, you know,
and um
having this content and have it be
comprehensible meaning you understand
it. So the idea is to use content that
you can understand but is still
challenging for you. So it's still like
a little above your level so that you're
learning new words, you're learning new
phrases, you're learning new vocabulary.
Your brain's having to kind of fill in
the gaps of things that you don't
understand when you read or you you
listen to whatever the content is. So
that's basically what you're doing right
now, right? You're watching this video.
Maybe you listen to my podcast. And what
it is is it's made specifically for a
specific level. This is a more advanced
video cuz I'm speaking at normal speed.
But you got the subtitles, right? And so
that's
a little bit more comprehensible. You're
able to like read the subtitles while
you're listening and so that makes it
more understandable. But for example, if
you watch my you know lower level videos
or if you listen to my podcast, you're
listening to content that's made for a
specific level that's lower than just
native level. So what that's good for is
that you actually you know, use content
that you can understand and you are
still being challenged. You're still
learning new words. You're still
learning new phrases. But it's
understandable. It's not something
that's just way above your level or
like just super boring and not authentic
and just like some textbook like
whatever text they put in there that's
not very interesting, right? So
unfortunately in schools
a lot of what you
consume in your English class is going
to be like really boring
like textbook style stories that don't
really interest anyone or they're like
little videos that you might watch that
really aren't that interesting. I
remember watching these Spanish in my
high school Spanish classes, my middle
school Spanish classes. Actually no, I
didn't
in middle school. That was just high
school. But in my high school Spanish
classes I remember watching like videos
that weren't that interesting or
whatever. So you know, the type of
content that we use is extremely
important because
if you use content that's interesting
for you, that's engaging for you that
you can understand but is still
challenging for you, that's going to be
like the optimal type of content that
you want to use. Man, it's kind of hard
to
like walk this fast and talk. You can
hear that I'm like breathing a little
bit harder. Hopefully you don't mind.
But yeah, using content like that is
going to be much, much more valuable for
you than using just the generic boring
content that might be too easy for you,
might be too hard for you, whatever it
may be. That content tends to be just
less useful overall, right? So the type
of content used in schools is often not
the best, right?
What else? What are the problems? Let me
think. I've got a few other ones that I
had in mind but I don't have my notes in
front of me so I kind of have to scour
my brain to try to remember what they
were. Yes, another issue is the speaking
practice is not very helpful, right?
Obviously speaking is like the hardest
part of learning a language for most
people, right? And so you would hope
that in these classes you would have
some like good, well designed, effective
speaking practice. But that's usually
not the case. At least in my experience
it was typical to do like role playing
and this role playing was not very
interesting. It's like all right, let's
pretend that you're the cashier, I'm the
person shopping here at the supermarket.
Let's interact, right? Obviously there
is something useful about that.
Obviously you can learn useful phrases,
useful words for that specific
situation. Maybe I'll slow down here so
I'm not walking so fast so I can talk
more easily. things that are good for
that situation.
But let's be honest. That's not the most
interesting type of speaking practice
and those types of things
like the words that you learn through
that exercise or whatever, they're not
going to stay in your head as like
easily as something that's much more
relevant to you. Like for example, if
you were to do speaking practice about
something that's actually really
important to you, it's really engaging
for you, it's really relevant to your
life you're probably going to learn and
remember those new words more easily. I
notice this a lot. For example, when I
do speaking practice when I'm learning
other languages,
what happens is I tend to focus a lot of
my early efforts on speaking about
things that are really important to me,
that are really relevant to my life. For
example, I might speak a lot about
language learning or I might speak a lot
about online business, content creation,
things that I do that I talk about on a
regular basis even in English and that
are interesting for me, that are
relevant for me. And so what tends to
happen is I learn a lot of new stuff,
words, phrases, grammar even, different
structures from talking about those
things cuz those things stay in my head.
I repeat them a lot cuz these are things
that I talk about a lot. I have a lot to
say about them so it kind of helps out
with the repetition where I'm speaking
more about them. These phrases are
sticking in my mind more. I don't know
if you guys want to kind of see the view
cuz you're kind of under me here but got
a nice big old park here pretty close to
my house. So this is pretty nice.
There's some kids over on the playground
so I'm trying to stay away from there.
But
yeah,
in terms of speaking practice the
speaking practice in these schools, in
these classes is just not that relevant,
not that useful. And because of that
it's not very memorable. The stuff that
you're learning doesn't stay with you as
easily, right? So that's a big issue. Uh
so speaking practice is, you know,
that's uh something that's lacking. Like
there there is speaking practice, but
it's not very good. It's not very
effective and it just doesn't help you
learn as much, right?
And then one other thing that I can
think of is just kind of a lack of
freedom when it comes to these classes
because as you probably know, when it
comes to learning a language, it's
really useful to be able to kind of have
flexibility and use content that's good
for you that perhaps might not be
interesting for someone else, but you
like it or, you know, whatever it may
be. Having this freedom to customize
like your consumption of English so that
it fits you, so that it's interesting
for you. This is something that's
obviously lacking in schools, right? So
obviously everyone's kind of forced to
read the same thing,
uh listen to the same thing, do the same
thing, you know, all this kind of stuff.
And yeah, I get it cuz we want
structure. But unfortunately, that means
that a lot of people are just kind of
tuned out. They're not really, you know,
engaged with what they're
um they're interacting with in the class
in terms of the content. And it probably
means that they're not retaining as much
information. It's just not good. Like
imagine if someone
forced you to use just like really
boring content for English, right? You
probably wouldn't be that excited to
learn English. Right? I hope that this
type of video is more interesting for
you than just some random boring
textbook or whatever it may be, right?
So I'm not saying that we need to just
like have no rules in the English class.
All I'm saying is there should be a
little more flexibility. Perhaps
students can use, you know, different
types of content. Uh not always have to
use the same exact thing if it's
interesting for one person, but not for
another person, right? And speaking of
textbooks, that's one other issue.
Uh I think there's just an over-reliance
on textbooks in English classes. Don't
get me wrong. There's nothing wrong with
textbooks. Textbooks are great. Uh
they're great like resources. You can
reference them if you want to learn
things about grammar, you want to learn
rules, you want to practice with things,
maybe learn vocabulary. Sometimes there
is like or they do have like good
interesting stories that could be good
uh comprehensible input. Not always, but
sometimes they have that as well. So
textbooks are great. However,
these classes tend to be like dependent
on these textbooks as like the primary
source of information for uh like our
primary source of interaction with the
language, you know, for the students.
And I don't think it should be like
that. Textbooks should be supplementary,
right? So obviously, it's good to
reference a textbook to learn different
things, practice with different rules if
that's what you're uh trying to do.
But the main foundation of your
learning, of course, is not going to
come from the textbook. It's not like,
all right, I'm going to learn all the
rules in the textbook and then I can use
all these rules
uh naturally in my own speech. It just
doesn't work that way, right? You guys
probably know what I'm talking about,
right? So
instead of that, you know, why not make
uh you know, uh comprehensible input the
foundation of the learning experience
even within the context of a classroom.
Have some relevant type of speaking
practice that's actually useful and
engaging. And then also use the textbook
as like a supplementary thing to help
with like certain grammar points and
help kind of give just a little bit of
guided structure through the the
fundamentals of the language or
whatever, right? So I think that would
be a better approach than like using the
textbook as the main learning resource,
right? Cuz I don't think anyone really
likes that that much. And it just
deprives people of the time uh like
during class to do other things that are
more important, right? Like the
listening comprehension and the the
relevant speaking practice, all of that.
One other issue, this one is kind of
hard to
really remedy, but the other issue is
that obviously most teachers in public
schools if they're teaching an English
class in some other country, they're not
a native speaker, right? And so because
of that, they're obviously not going to
pronounce words correctly all the time.
They're obviously going to say things
that are wrong. And, you know, that's
just kind of how it goes. That's not
like a knock on these English teachers.
I'm not trying to insult these English
teachers. Obviously, you know, they're
doing the best they can, right? But
obviously, there is the issue of people
in these classes that just repeat what
they hear the teacher say. And
obviously, if the teacher pronounces
something wrong, you know, the students
are going to say it that wrong way,
right? They're looking at the teacher as
the authority, so they're going to say
it wrong like the teacher does. But
again, that's a little bit harder to
remedy because you can't have a native
teacher in all these classes. But what I
would say is if you are like a teacher,
uh an English teacher in one of these
classes, it's really important to
acknowledge this, right? We don't want
to get so prideful. Like if I were
teaching Spanish, let's say, in the US,
I would never want to be so prideful to
say like, oh no, like I'm, you know, the
the way that I'm saying it is exactly
the way that someone from Mexico would
say it cuz it's not, right? Even though
I don't have a terrible accent when I
speak Spanish, I do not say things the
same way that a Mexican does, right? And
there's nothing wrong with that. I'm a
second language learner, right? I
learned it as an adult, obviously. So
when it comes to like, you know, a
someone teaching English in another
country and they're not a native
speaker, they should have that same
attitude of not thinking, well, I'm the
teacher, so everything I say is right
and correct. You know, that's just not
the case, right? We need to acknowledge
that. And so if you can acknowledge that
and if you can also like communicate
that to the students and perhaps use
other content like that would be from
native speakers, like videos and audios
and things like that, that would serve
as like instructional um you know,
material or just listening practice
beyond just your own speaking, obviously
that would be good as well. Like if I
were teaching Spanish in the US in a
class, I wouldn't want their listening
practice to be like just all just from
me. Like it wouldn't it shouldn't be
100% me speaking, right? Because
obviously I'm not a native speaker.
They're going to be missing a lot if I'm
the one that's like 100% of their
listening content, right? Whereas in
English, obviously I have no problem
doing that cuz I'm a native speaker.
Okay? So I think the same thing goes for
someone teaching English in another
country.
It'd be good for them to just, you know,
be humble, obviously know that they're
not going to say everything correct uh
correctly. And then also kind of utilize
other content to supplement, you know,
what they're saying to the students, you
know, like native content. And, you
know, help them help students find
native content that's good for them,
that will serve as good listening
practice for them.
My thoughts are really scattered right
now. It's kind of nice uh to do videos
like this. It's just a little bit um
little bit outside my uh comfort zone.
But if you guys like this, I'll try to
do this a little bit more often, but
there's a few other people walking
around. I'm trying to avoid them. Trying
to go to places where I can just walk
freely and not uh
not uh need to lower my voice cuz
makes me a little bit embarrassed to
like talk really loud here at the park
filming myself or whatever. But um yeah,
those are some of the issues that I
think. And then, you know, the remedies
would just be to kind of,
you know,
mitigate those issues. Make those issues
less of a problem, right? Don't rely too
much on textbooks. Use comprehensible
input. Uh teach students how to learn
English. That's probably the the biggest
thing, the biggest uh solution or
biggest um help to the classroom would
be to actually teach students how to
learn on their own, right? If you can
teach how uh teach a student how they
can actually utilize their time at home
that they have to learn English, utilize
it the right way, you know, that's
golden, right? That would be a really,
really good thing for someone to learn
how to learn English on their own
because the majority of our learning
doesn't come from that high school
English class. It comes from all the
stuff that we're listening to, that
we're reading, uh that we're watching on
our own. And of course, the speaking
practice that we do, you know, whether
it be, you know, with other uh people in
our daily lives,
uh other people online or whoever it is.
Right? Those are the things that really,
you know, that's like the foundation of
our learning, right? So I think that uh
even though it's not my expertise like
the classroom setting, I'm more of a
one-on-one type teacher, uh I think that
these are still valid ideas even though
I'm not an expert. I think that um I'm
speaking just kind of from experience,
from what I've heard from uh students
that have talked to me like about issues
uh with their English class experience
or whatever. So I don't know what you
guys think. Maybe you can leave a
comment down below and let me know what
you think about that. Uh what are some
of the uh struggles that you came across
learning English in a high school
classroom setting or whatever. And let
me know what you think about this type
of video.
>> [laughter]
>> Obviously, I'm breathing a little bit
more heavily. I think I just need to
walk more slowly. That would be better.
Cuz I'm I was like walking really fast
before. Uh so if I walk more slowly,
maybe it'll be a little a little bit
more natural. But uh this is fun for me,
so hopefully you guys like this. Uh
remember that if you want more advanced
content, if you want all of my advanced
episodes, so I've already recorded like
a hundred of them or something like
that. You can get them all just by
becoming a Listening Time Family Member.
And you'll still get two new ones every
single month after that. So it's a
really, really great deal. Uh the link
down below, if you go down and click on
that, you can sign up to become a
Listening Time Family Member and you'll
get those. Also, check out my US
Conversations Podcast. In that podcast,
I talk to uh different English teachers
>> [music]
>> from all over the country. It's a lot of
fun. It's great practice for your
listening. These are authentic
conversations. I give you the transcript
for it, so you can follow along more
easily. If you want that, that link is
also down below. All right. Thank you
all for listening, and I'll talk to you
in the next video.